<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Athenian babler a sermon preached at St. Maries in Oxforde, the 9. of Iuly, 1626, being Act-Sunday / by Humphry Sydenham ...</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S530</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22599749</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22599749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1758:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Athenian babler a sermon preached at St. Maries in Oxforde, the 9. of Iuly, 1626, being Act-Sunday / by Humphry Sydenham ...</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.A. and T. Favvcet, for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-F⁴ G².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Central Library (Bristol, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVII, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25625:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> ATHENIAN <hi>Babler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT St. MARIES in <hi>Oxforde,</hi> the 9. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1626. being ACT-<hi>Sunday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Humphry Sydenham,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Fellow of WADHAM-Colledge in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by B. A. and T. FAVVCET, for IOHN PARKER. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25625:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25625:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HOPEFVLL EXPECTATION, BOTH OF HIS NAME, AND Countrey, <hi>Sir</hi> HVGH PORTMAN, <hi>BARONET, this.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY HONOVR'D S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oweuer</hi> the publiſhing of other Labours may enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mee to <hi>Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> this cannot but touch vpon <hi>Humilitie,</hi> ſince I haue expoſed that to the <hi>Eye</hi> onely of a <hi>Nation,</hi> which I had formerly to the <hi>Eare</hi> of a <hi>World,</hi> a <hi>Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie;</hi> a <hi>World</hi> more Glorious then that which inuolues it, by how much it exceeds
<pb facs="tcp:25625:3"/>the other, in her <hi>Iudgement,</hi> in her <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and (what is Noble, too) her <hi>incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement;</hi> of the latter, I had ſome taſte in the deliuery of <hi>this,</hi> when I was a fitter object of her Pitie, then approbation, whether ſhee reflected on <hi>Minde,</hi> or <hi>Body,</hi> my <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> or <hi>Mee.</hi> But that was the extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>her</hi> goodneſſe, nothing that my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe could expect, or point at, but the <hi>Mercy</hi> of my <hi>worthyer</hi> Friends, amongst whome, as, you were then pleaſed to approue it, ſo, now vouchſafe both to peruſe and Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; In that you ſhall glorifie the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of him, who lookes no higher, then the honour of this title,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend that euer ſerues you HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25625:3"/>
            <head>THE ATHENIAN BABLER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Text. ACTS, 17. Verſ. 18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Some ſaid; what will this Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſay?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Life of a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an the Apoſtle calls a continuall warfare; The life of a true Apoſtle the Chriſtian calls a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Martyrdome; Each act of it hath a bloody ſceane, but not a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; A few wounds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet terminate his miſery, though they begin his glory. There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tough breathings required to the Coeleſtiall race; many a bleeding ſcarre to the good Fight, ſweatings, wreſtlings, tuggings numberleſſe to the crowne of Glory. PAVL had long ſince begun the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25625:4"/>courſe and finiſht it, and can ſhew you a platforme of all the ſufferings; the ſcrowle is ready drawne with his owne hand,<note place="margin">Verſ. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28.</note> you may peruſe it if you pleaſe, 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. where crueltie ſeemes to bee metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall, and torment accurate, perſecution tumbles on perſecution, as a billow on a billow, this on the necke of that; one ſeales not the truth of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, many ſhall.<note place="margin">Act. 14. v. 10.19.</note> Hee was but now at <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> where hee cured a Cripple, and hee is ſtoned for it; by and by at <hi>Philippi</hi> hee caſts out a Diuell,<note place="margin">Act. 16.18.23.</note> and hee is ſcourged. Heere's not all; ſufferings of the body are not load enough for an Apoſtle; if hee loue his Lord and Maſter (as hee ought) hee muſt haue ſome of reputation too; hee that hath beene ſo long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Laſh of the hand, muſt now feele that of the tongue too: Buffettings are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for Diſciples, they muſt haue reuilings alſo for the name of IESVS, PAVL therefore ſhall now to <hi>Athens</hi> (the eye of the learned world and ſeate of the Philoſopher) where hee meets with language as peruerſe as the Religion, and amongſt many falſe ones, findes no entertainment for the true; The mention of a IESVS Crucified ſtands not with the Faith of an <hi>Athenian,</hi> nor a ſtory of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with his Philoſophie. The Altar there conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the <hi>vnknowne</hi> will not ſo ſoone ſmoake to the <hi>jealous God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.23.</note> The glorious Statues of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> cannot yet bee tranſlated to the forme of a <hi>Nazarite.</hi> 'Tis not a bare relation can plant CHRIST at <hi>Athens,</hi> it muſt bee Reaſon, the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and ſtrength of ſome powerfull Argument, and to this purpoſe PAVL was but now in hot Diſputation with the <hi>Iewes</hi> there in the <hi>Synagogue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17. v. 17.</note> By this time he hath diſparcht; for loe yonder where hee ſtands in earneſt diſcourſe with the people in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25625:4"/>
               <hi>Market?</hi> The tumult is inlarged, and the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> already tickled with the expectation of ſome noueltie; Anon, the Gowne beſets him, and all the rigid Sects of the Philoſophers; as the throng in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, ſo doth the Cry; On that ſide, Cenſure, — <hi>Some ſayd hee was a ſetter forth of ſtrange Gods,</hi> on this ſide, Preiudice, — <hi>And ſome ſaid, what will this Babler ſay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the diuiſion of which tumult wilt pleaſe you to obſerue mine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The perſons Prejudicate,</hi> maskt heere vnder a doubtfull Pronoune, <hi>Quidam - ſome,</hi> - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, - <hi>ſome ſayd.</hi> - 2. <hi>The perſon prejudic'd,</hi> cloathed in a terme of obloquy and diſhonour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> - <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, - What will this Babler ſay?</hi> Thus the Field ſtands pitcht where wee may view the parts, as the perſons, In a double ſquadron, no more. PAVL and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in one part of the <hi>Battalio; Epicures, Stoickes</hi> with their Philoſophie, in the other, the reſt are but lookers on, no ſharers in the conflict. Heeres all; All that's naturall from the words, and not wreſted; For (mine owne part) I'le not pull Scripture into pieces, digging for particulars which are not offred, for that were to torment a Text, not diuide it. I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect nothing that is forc'd, loue Fluentneſſe, and (what the maieſtie of this place may (perchance) looke ſowre on) plainneſſe. Howeuer, at this time, I haue a little endeuoured that way, that thoſe of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> and <hi>Epheſus</hi> may aſwell heare PAVL as theſe of <hi>Athens.</hi> I come not now to play with the quaint eare but to rubbe it, nor to cheriſh the dancing expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of thoſe <hi>Athenians</hi> which cry - <hi>Newes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 17. v. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Newes,</hi> - but to foyle it. And this is well enough for a <hi>Babler,</hi> that's the doome at <hi>Athens,</hi> mine, now, and juſtly too. I may not expect a greater mercy of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25625:5"/>the tongue thence, then an Apoſtle had, eſpecially when a <hi>Stoicke</hi> raignes in it. Whoſe Religion (for the moſt part) is but ſnarling, and a maine peece of his learning, Cenſure; But let's heare firſt what hee can ſay of the <hi>Babler,</hi> next, what the <hi>Babler</hi> will ſay. I begin with the perſons preiudicate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Some ſayd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>what ſome?</hi> The front of this verſe preſents them both in their qualitie, and number; <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi> What of all Sects? No. -<note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Certayne Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> - of old, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſince, by the modeſtie of PY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THAGORAS a little degraded of that height, as if it trenched too neere vpon ambition to entitle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues immediatly vnto Wiſdome, but to the loue of it, and therefore now, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet ſtill of venerable eſteeme amongſt the <hi>Athenians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In cap. 17. Act.</note> ARETIVS calls them their <hi>Diuines;</hi> BRENTIVS, their <hi>Patriarkes</hi> and their <hi>Prophets,</hi> Each word they ſpake was as canonicall as Text, and they themſelues both Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of it, and of the people. Of theſe there were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Sects, two (heere) ſpecified. <hi>Epicures, Stoickes;</hi> theſe were extreames in the rules both of their life, and tenent; the <hi>Epicure</hi> in the defect, the <hi>Stoicke</hi> in the exceſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> in cap. 17. Act.</note> Betweene them both were the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticks</hi> and the <hi>Academicks,</hi> better mixt and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified in their opinion, ſtooping neyther to the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the one, nor the auſteritie of the other; but of theſe no mention in the Text. The <hi>Areopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gites</hi> (intimated in the foot of this Chapter) were not <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> but the <hi>Athenian</hi> Iudges, ſome ſay, others, their <hi>Conſuls,</hi> or their <hi>Senatours:</hi> In the ſtreet of <hi>Mars</hi> (where the <hi>Athenians</hi> brought PAVL,<note place="margin">Act. 17. v. 22.</note> and enquired of his Doctrine) was their Tribunall, where they ſate vpon their more weighty affaires, and,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> not. ibid.</note> of old, arraigned SOCRATES and condemned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25625:5"/>him of impietie. But I haue no quarrell to theſe, ſince I finde they had none to the Apoſtle; The <hi>Stoicke</hi> and the <hi>Epicure</hi> are the ſole incendiaries and ringleaders of the tumult, whom the very Text points out in this, - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> - <hi>ſome ſayd,</hi> - men as oppoſite in their opinion, as to the truth; one ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his chiefe happineſſe in the pleaſure of the Body, the other in the vertues of the Mind. The <hi>Epicure</hi> attributed too much to voluptuouſneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> in cap. 17. Act.</note> the <hi>Stoicke</hi> to the want of it; that would haue a vacuitie of griefe both in mind, and ſence; this taught his - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> - a nullitie of all affections in eyther. Theſe are the broad and common Differences in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and ſuch as heere tread oppoſite to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Saint PAVL; but there are others more cryticall and nice, which not finding touch'd by the pen of the Holy Ghoſt, I preſum'd to enquire after in their owne Schooles, in <hi>Zeno's Stoä</hi> for one, and in <hi>Epicurus</hi> Garden for the other. A trauaile ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vnneceſſary for <hi>Athens</hi> amongſt <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> where they are daily canuaſt. Yet (perchance) there may bee - <hi>ſome Nobles heere of</hi> Bereä, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>17</label> 
               <hi>and Chiefe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of</hi> Theſſalonica,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>which haue receiued</hi> PAVL <hi>with all willingneſſe</hi> - which know them not. I ſhall bee onely your remembrancer, their informer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epicures</hi> (for I begin with them, they haue the precedence in the Text) challenge both name, and pedigree, from EPICVRVS the founder, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Sect. Hee was borne at <hi>Athens</hi> ſeauen yeares after the Death of PLATO, where he liued, taught, dyed. Hee wrote 300. Bookes in his owne Art, without reference to a ſecond Pen, and (what is ſtrange) obſeruation; no ſentence, no precept of Philoſopher, but his owne; thoſe of DEMOCRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVS, <hi>de Atomis,</hi> and of ARISTIPPVS, <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25625:6"/>DIONISIVS HALICARNASSEVS cals his.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Hiſt.</note> His deportment and way of carriage in matters of Moralitie was very remarkeable.<note place="margin">Lib. de Epicur.</note> 
               <hi>In Parentes pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, in Fratres Beneficentia, in Serues manſuetudo.</hi> ('Tis the triple commendation LAERTIVS giues him,) And in lieu of theſe, and the like vertues, his Countrey afterwards erected many brazen Statues, and ATHENAEVS wrote certayne Epitaphes to the perpetuall embalming both of his name and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Hee was one it ſeemes more irreguler in his tenent, then his life, abſtenious hee was, moderate, in his repaſt,<note place="margin">A Ferc ſic in Lorum.</note> in his deſires, - <hi>Oleribus vtens exiguis,</hi> HIEROME ſayes, and hee confeſſes himſelfe in his Epiſtles, that Temperance was his Feaſt, the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtayre of it,<note place="margin">Allexand ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Genae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Dierum. Cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Parcemonie: <hi>Aquâ contentus &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentâ.</hi> His place of teaching was in Gardens, and the manner not onely to the capacitie, but the Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his hearer.</p>
            <p>The whole Fabricke of his precepts hee builds vpon this double ground; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one on Mans part, that hee is compoſed of a double ſubſtance, a Body, and a Soule, and both theſe mortall; yea, the Soule vaniſht ſooner then the Body; For when the Soule is breathed out, the Body yet remaines the ſame and the proportion of parts, perfect. <hi>Anima mox vt exierit veluti fumus vento diuerberata, diſſoluitur,</hi> But the Soule is no ſooner ſeperate then blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, like ſmoake ſcattered by the wind. So S. AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTINE relates the opinion in his Tract. <hi>De Epic. &amp; Stoic.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> On this foundation was raiſed their great opinion, that Mans chiefeſt happineſſes conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the pleaſure of the Body. <hi>The rest of that was the end of all Bleſſedneſſe, For to this purpoſe doe wee all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Epiſtol. ad Herodetum.</note> 
               <hi>that wee may neyther bee diſturbed nor grieued,</hi> ('tis EPICVRVS owne Doctrine.)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25625:6"/>Yet euery pleaſure is not ſo magnified, as that of the Pallate by ſuperfluitie, of the Body by effeminate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; <hi>But, when after a long tolleration of ſorrow a greater pleaſure enſues, when the Body is no more bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with griefe, the Mind vntost and free from all waues of perturbation, there was the true Happineſſe. Hee was bleſſed that enjoyed thoſe Delights in preſent; future, they neither beleeued, nor cared for, Death was the ſlaughterman of all:</hi> And therefore SENECA calls the Schoole of the <hi>Epicures; Delicatam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Benefic.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braticam, apud quos virtus voluptatis miniſtra.</hi> For if the Soule alſo periſheth with the Body, the dirge and <hi>requiem</hi> that they ſing, is <hi>Ede, Bibe, Lude,</hi> Eate and Drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall Dye; and after Death what pleaſure? And therefore wee find their vſuall <hi>Epicaedium</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, - <hi>Death is nothing to vs, for what is diſſolued wants ſence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Pyrron. Hypotyp. cap. <hi>24</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and what wants ſence is nothing to vs. For if Man bee compoſed of Body and Soule, and Death bee the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of both, the burthen of their ſong runnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, Cùm ſumus, nòn eſt mors, cùm autèm mors eſt, non ſumus,</hi> ſo SEXTVS EMPIRICVS; More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, they would haue the Soule a kind of body, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (ſay they) <hi>it would neyther doe nor ſuffer, Incorporeum,</hi> with them, is all one with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>acuum;</hi> and therefore, <hi>the Soule</hi> (they ſayd) <hi>was compoſed of Atomes, and when the Atoms in a man were diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then the Soule dyed,</hi> as EPICVRVS himſelfe in his Epiſtle to HERODOTVS.</p>
            <p>The other foundation is on Gods part, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for the <hi>Epicure</hi> grants there is a GOD, but denies his Prouidence; howbeit, vnder a glorious colour - <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ad Coeli cardines obambulare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gualt. in Locum</note> 
               <hi>&amp; nulla tangi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium curâ,</hi> as if, forſooth, it would not ſtand with the maieſtie of the world to regard what is done in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25625:7"/>thoſe ſublunary parts,<note place="margin">Jn Apoleg. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. ginits. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> and ſo make God (as TER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVLLIN complaines) <hi>Otioſum, &amp; inexercitum neminem in humanis rebus,</hi> - happely conceiting it might detract ſomewhat from his delight and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to moleſt himſelfe with the care of this nether World. Aboue all things this moued him moſt, - <hi>Homines Religioſos,</hi> - that the moſt Religious men were moſt of all afflicted, whereas thoſe which did eyther wholly neglect the Gods, or ſerue them but at their pleaſure, came into no misfortune, or at leaſt no misfortune like other men. And, in fine, <hi>Ipſa eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Templa fulminibus conſtagrari,</hi> - hee obſerued that the Temples alſo rayſed for the honour of the Gods, and dedicated to their ſeruice were often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times burnt with fire from Heauen. Out of which premiſſes the ſilly Heathen gathers this deſperate Concluſion:<note place="margin">Allexand ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Gena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Dierum. Cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Surely the Almighty walketh in the height of Heauen, and judgeth not; Tuſh, GOD ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not for thoſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stoickes</hi> (ſo deriued from <hi>Stoä</hi> where ZENO taught, the Maſter of that Sect) were of a more ſowre and contracted brow; their ſeuerity drew their name into a Prouerbe, <hi>Stoicum ſupercilium, grauitas Stoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca:</hi> their Precepts were for the moſt part but a Syſteame of harſh and auſteere paradoxes. <hi>A wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is then bleſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tull. <hi>5.</hi> de Fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; <hi>1.</hi> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note> 
               <hi>when vnder the greateſt torments.</hi> Merellus <hi>liues not more happily then</hi> Regulus. <hi>A wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is free from all paſſions. Hee is a foole that doth commiſerate his Friend in diſtreſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lypſius in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduct ad St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am Phyleſoph.</note> 
               <hi>Mercy and Pitie are diſeaſes of the minde, and one with the species and perturbations of griefe, Mentall ſickneſſes diſturbe no wiſe mans health. Hee can norther erre, nor bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, nor deceiue, nor lye. Hee is alone to bee reputed rich, a Maſter of his owne libertie, a King, without ſinne, equall to GOD himſelfe; Hoc eſt ſummum
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25625:7"/>bonum, quod ſi occupas, incipis Deorum ſocius eſſe, non ſupplex,</hi> it is SENECA'S <hi>Stoyiciſme,</hi> in his 31. <hi>Epiſtle.</hi> In all Vertues they held a paritie,<note place="margin">Tull. <hi>1.</hi> de not. Deorum.</note> and ſo in Sinnes too, <hi>Hee no more faultie that kills a Man, then hee that cuts off a Dogs necke.</hi> Touching GOD and the nature of him, they ſtrangely varyed. Some thought him - <hi>an immortall liuing Creature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tull. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de nat. Deorum.</note> 
               <hi>a perfect rationall and a bleſſed;</hi> others granted him a <hi>Beeing and Prouidence;</hi> but this Prouidence they vaſſall to their <hi>Stoyicall fate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diogen. Laert. in vita Zeno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> and make Gods gouernment not free and voluntary, but neceſſitated and compelled. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Deus ipſe ſati neceſſitate conſtrictus cum Coeli ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china violenter ferretur.</hi> (ſo CALVIN.)<note place="margin">In 17. cap. Act.</note> Touching Man, they taught that his chiefeſt Happineſſe was placed in the Minds vertue, which opinion though it ſhew faire and glorious,<note place="margin">In Locum.</note> tends but to this - <hi>Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis mortalem faelicitatis ſuae artificem eſſe poſſe,</hi> (ſayes BVLLINGER.) Euery man ſhould bee the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ſquarer out of his owne Happineſſe; and thus weake man is hereby blowne vp with a proud confidence, that, being vertuous he ſhould bee ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſpoyles of God, - <hi>Eſt aliquid quo ſapiens antecedat Deum, ille naturae beneficio, non ſuo ſapiens est.</hi> I forbeare to tranſlate the proud Blaſphemy, it is SENECA'S in his 53. Epiſtle. But me thinkes this vaunting <hi>Stoicke</hi> might eaſily haue beene taken downe by his owne Principles, for aske but any of them, how long their ſoule ſhall enioy that ſuppoſed happineſſe. TVLLY makes anſwere for them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> de Finibus.</note> - <hi>Diù manſuros aiunt animos, ſemper negant,</hi> - Like long-liued Crowes, they laſt out ſome yeares after the bodies Death; but by their owne confeſſions grow old continually, and dye at laſt; and then wherein may the <hi>Stoicke</hi> bragge more then the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Laert. lib. de E. picue.</note> In this, little. They both held, <hi>the Soule was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25625:8"/>of it ſelfe a body;</hi> the <hi>Stoicke</hi> did extend it a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then, obnoxious to corruption, too. And yet ANTIPATER, and POSSIDONIVS (chiefe members of that Sect) ſayd, the Soule was a hot ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for this made vs to moue and breath; And all ſoules ſhould endure till that heate were extinguiſht, CLEANTHES ſayd,<note place="margin">Sextus Emper. Pyrron. Hypol. cap <hi>24.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but CHRYSIPPVS, onely wiſe-mens. Thus ſome are as giddy in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as ſottiſh; others, as deteſtable, as giddy; one dotes on the world, and would haue it to bee - <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal rationale,</hi> - The vniuerſe muſt haue a Soule, that immortall, and the parts thereof, <hi>Animantium ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</hi> A ſecond falls in loue with Vertues, and would haue them to bee <hi>glorious liuing Creatures;</hi> but this foole SENECA laſhes with an - <hi>O triſtes ineptias, ridiculae ſunt,</hi> in his 113. Epiſtle. A third adores the Starres, and would haue them <hi>nouriſht, the Sunne from the Sea, the Moone from the leſſer waters.</hi> A fourth growes ſalacious, and hot, and would haue a <hi>communitie of Wiues, to Wiſe men, of Strumpets, to the reſidue.</hi> A fifth, yet more diueliſh, will haue <hi>a libertie of Bed from the Father to the Daughter, from the Mother to the Sonne, from the Brother to the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſo backe againe:</hi> and to make all compleatly heatheniſh (and I tremble to breath it in a Pulpit) <hi>A Sonne may participate of the body of his liue Mother, and eate the fleſh of his dead Father.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabile;</hi> Cryes SEXTVS EMPERICVS - <hi>Zeno ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probat quod apud nos Sodomitae,</hi> - in his 3. Booke <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roniarum Hypotyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Cap. 24.</p>
            <p>Thus, with as much breuitie as I could, I haue traced out the principall poſitions of theſe diuided Sects. Worthy ones no doubt, to bandy againſt the ſacred Fundamentals of an Apoſtle, yet if it now pleaſe you to follow them, - <hi>E stoä, &amp; hortis, in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogam,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25625:8"/>- From their Gallery and Garden where they taught, into their Synagogue, you ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them there all flocked together about S. PAVL,<note place="margin">Act. 17. v. 17.</note> and (as the Text deſcribes it) <hi>encountring</hi> him. Heere is juſt matter for obſeruation, if not for won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Epicures, Stoickes,</hi> men which jarre aſmuch as any that beare the name of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> can doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, are ready (neuertheleſſe) to meet in a tumult and joyne forces againſt an Apoſtle, ſtrange, did wee not know that the wiſedome of this world were enmitie againſt GOD, and that - CHRIST <hi>vnto the Jewes a ſtumbling Blocke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>vnto the Grecians fooliſhneſſe.</hi> What the ground was which ſhould occaſion this aſſault, SAVGVSTINE conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures to bee (and it is not repugnant to the drift of the Text) <hi>Quid faciat beatam vitam?</hi> What might make a man moſt happie? The <hi>Epicure</hi> hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers;<note place="margin">Caluin. in Locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>Voluptas corporis,</hi> the pleaſure, but with this limitation, the honeſt pleaſure of the body. The <hi>Stoicke</hi> hee ſayth, - <hi>Virtus,</hi> - The vertue of the mind;<note place="margin">Auguſt. Tract. de Epicur. &amp; Stoicis, cap <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> the Apoſtle replies - <hi>Donum Dei,</hi> it is the guift of GOD: LYRA addes, that from thence the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele led them to the Reſurrection.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyra</hi> in cap 17. Act.</note> For the <hi>Epicures</hi> joy could laſt no longer then his ſubiect; his bliſſe muſt dye with his body; and the <hi>Stoickes</hi> foreſaw not the Soules immortalitie, and therefore could not promiſe euerlaſting Happineſſe. But the Apoſtle hee preacheth a Reſurection of body and ſoule, and by that Eternall life,<note place="margin">Act 17.18.</note> and ſo by conſequence euerlaſting Happineſſe through CHRIST, both of Soule and Body. This ſeemes to haue been the ſubiect of their Diſpute, but their Arguments I can by no meanes collect; Be like they were ſo ſilly, that they were not thought worthy to bee enrolled amongſt thoſe more noble Acts of the Apoſtles, onely their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25625:9"/>that is ſo notorious that it may not bee omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For on what ſide ſoeuer the victorie goes, theirs is the tryumph; the cry runnes with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian,</hi> the Philoſopher hath non-pluſt the Diuine, and the Apoſtle <hi>bables.</hi> Thus the wicked haue bent their bowe and ſhot their arrowes, euen bitter words, bitter words againſt the Church and her true members in all Ages. The naturall man led on by the dull light of reaſon, making Philoſophie his Starre, endeauours with thoſe weake twinklings thoſe leſſer influences to obſcure the glory of the greater light, that of Diuine truth; ſo it was in the firſt dawne and riſing of the Church. IANNES and IAMBRES, the great Magitians of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood MOSES working miracles before PHARAOH. But all the ſpels of Magicke with their blacke power, neuer wrought ſo miſchieuouſly againſt the Church as the ſubtle inchantments of the Philoſopher. Chriſtianitie neuer felt ſuch wounds, as from the Schoole of the <hi>Athenian.</hi> The <hi>Seminarie</hi> of the wrangling Artiſt; the Epicure, <hi>Stoicke, Platoniſt;</hi> they were Philoſophers, that's enough; they not onely ſtrugled to oppoſe Fundamentals of Faith, but to deſtroy them. Euery age of the Church, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt euery place of it will giue vs a world of Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; one <hi>Alexandria</hi> affoords at. <hi>Aetius</hi> and a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mophylus,</hi> againſt CHRIST, one <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> a <hi>Macedonius,</hi> and an <hi>Eurox,</hi> againſt the Holy Ghoſt; One <hi>Epheſus,</hi> an <hi>Anthemius,</hi> and a <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi> againſt the Virgin MARY; One <hi>Athens</hi> (heere) an <hi>Epicure,</hi> and a <hi>Stoicke,</hi> againſt PAVL; Nay, the ſophiſtry of one peruerſe but nimble Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant, hath coſt more liues then are now breathing in the Chriſtian world, and opened ſuch a ſluce and Arch through the body of the Eaſterne Church,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25625:9"/>which was not ſtopt againe almoſt in the current of 300. yeares, when downe it blood ran ſwiftly from the butcheries of <hi>Valens</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and the limbes, the thouſand limbs of ſlaughtered Infants ſwam with the violence of the Torrent, euen then when Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity groaned vnder the mercileſſe inuentions and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tortures of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Maſſacre and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Philoſophers were the firſt <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of that Hereſie, and hence I ſuppoſe was that Edict of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that as a badge and character of their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they ſhould bee no more called <hi>Arrians,</hi> but <hi>Porphirians,</hi> the venemous brood of their curſed Maſter, and one that then blew the coale to moſt combuſtions of the Primitiue Church; For at <hi>the Councell of</hi> Nice (the place, and meanes ordayned by that good Emperour for the ſuppreſſion of <hi>Arrius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sozom. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 3.25.) ſome, if not of his name yet of his profeſſion, (for they were Phyloſophers) trooped thither in droues and multitudes, not onely to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Biſhops, but to vpbraid them. <hi>Odio imflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati quod ſuperſtitioſa Gentilium religio antiquari caeperat,</hi> - as <hi>Ruffinus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. And before that (in the Apoſtles time) about the yeare of CHRIST 75. they went about from Citie to Citie with this pretext onely to reforme publique miſdemeanors, and to that purpoſe had certayne Sermons to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for rectifying their Conuerſation in morrall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and ſo ſeemed induſtrious to reduce them to a better forme, but the maine proiect was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front the Apoſtles doctrine, and eſtabliſh them more immoueably in the former ſuperſtition of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, thus did <hi>Dyon, Apollonius, Euphrates, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>métrius, Muſonius, Epictetus, Lucian,</hi> and others, as <hi>Baronius</hi> in his firſt Tome 777 pag. nay,<note place="margin">Ad Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> the very dregs of them (ſayth the Antiquarie) the <hi>Cynieke,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:25625:10"/>and the <hi>Epicure,</hi> ſo violent (heere) againſt PAVL. <hi>Hos prae caeteris infestos ſenſit Chriſtiana religio.</hi> - Theſe were the heathen <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> the chiefe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and ſpeare-men againſt the Chriſtian Faith, when at <hi>Rome</hi> the ſides of that Religion were ſtrucke through with their blaſphemous Declamations, <hi>Et petulantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eorum calumnijs &amp; dicterijs miſerè proſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baron. Ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>164.</hi>
               </note> the ſame <hi>Baronius</hi> in his ſecond Tome, pag. 154. Thus all violent oppoſitions of Chriſtian truth had their firſt conception in the wombe of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie;</hi> The Fathers which traffick't with the tumults of thoſe times, ſaid in effect as much, - <hi>Omnes haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſubornauit Philoſophia,</hi> - MARCION came out of the Schoole of our <hi>Stoicke,</hi> CELSVS, of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picure,</hi> VALENTINVS, of that of PLATO; all hereſies were the flouriſhings and trimmings of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Learning. <hi>Inde Aeones, &amp; formae neſcio quae, &amp; Trinitas hominis apud <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinum.</hi> Thence thoſe <hi>Aeones</hi> (I know not what <hi>Idaeas,</hi>) and that triple man in <hi>Valentinus,</hi> hee was a <hi>Platonist.</hi> Thence <hi>Marcions</hi> quiet God, it came from the <hi>Stoickes;</hi> And the Soule ſhould be made ſubiect to Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, - is an obſeruation of the <hi>Epicures,</hi> and the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the Reſurrection, the joynt opinion of their whole Schooles.<note place="margin">Lib. de Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. aduerſ. Haereſ.</note> And when their - <hi>Materia prima</hi> is matcht with God, it is <hi>Zeno's</hi> Diſcipline, and when God is ſaid to bee a fiery Subſtance, <hi>Heraclitus</hi> hath a finger in it,<note place="margin">Comment. in Nahu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> thus <hi>Tertullian.</hi> S. <hi>Hierome</hi> keepes on the Catalogue - <hi>inde Eunomins prefert.</hi> Thence <hi>Eunomius</hi> drew his poyſon againſt the Eternitie of the Sonne of God, For <hi>whatſoeuer is begotten and borne before it was begotten, was not;</hi> Thence <hi>Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> blockes vp all hope of pardon for offences on Gods part, that hee might take away repentance and all ſuite for it, on ours. Thence <hi>Manichaeus</hi> dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25625:10"/>God, and <hi>Sabellius</hi> ſingle perſon; and to be ſhort - <hi>De illis fontibus vniuerſa dogmata argumentationum ſuarum riuulos trahunt: - Menandrians, Saturnians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Johan. Baptist. Chriſpus de Ethnic. Philoſ. Caute Legend. Quinar. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baſilidians, Ammonians, Proclians, Iulians,</hi> and the reſidue of that curſed Rabble, had from thence their conception, birth, nouriſhment, continuance. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the great Doctor of the Gentiles, writing pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely of their Wiſedome, alledgeth no other reaſon why they were not wiſe vnto Saluation, but <hi>the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this World. The world through Wiſedome knew not God.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. And therefore hee preſcribes the <hi>Colloſſians</hi> a - <hi>Cauete nè vos ſeducat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.4.</note> - Take heed leaſt any man ſpoyle you through Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie and vaine deceit. <hi>Fuerat Athenis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Praeſcript. aduerſ Haereſ.</note> S. PAVL had bin at <hi>Athens</hi> (ſayth <hi>Tertullian,</hi>) and knew by his often encounter there, how deſperately ſecular and prophane Knowledge wounded Diuine truth. Inſomuch, that the Father is of opinion. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nâ hac ſententiâ omnes haereſes damnari,</hi> in his 5. Booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> 19. Chapter.</p>
            <p>But whileſt wee goe about to vindicate our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, let vs not bee too iniurious to the <hi>Philoſopher;</hi> The <hi>Epicure</hi> and the <hi>Stoicke</hi> had their Droſſe and rubbiſh, yet they had their Siluer too, which had paſt the fornace, tryed and purified enough for the practice of a Chriſtian. Though they had Huskes and Acornes for their Swine, yet they had Bread for Men. It was not their Philoſophie was ſo peſtilent, but the vſe of it; our Apoſtle reprehends not the true, but the vaine; no doubt there is that which is Sanctified, as well as the Adulterate, otherwiſe the Fathers would neuer haue ſtiled Diuinitie, <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie;</hi> That is a glorious ray ſent downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the Father of Light; This but ſtrange Fire, ſome <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſtole thence, and infuſed into a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25625:11"/>peece of babling clay which circumuents weake men, and vnder a ſhadow and pretext of Wiſedome, oftentimes carries away probabilitie for truth. And it was this latter that inflamed the youth of AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTINE to the ſtudy of it; but he was ſoone cool'd when hee deſcried the other;<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> then - <hi>Nomen Chriſts non erat ibi,</hi> - in the 3. of his <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> And the <hi>words</hi> - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>were not now to bee read in the great Peripateti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> - Inſomuch, that that former aſſeueration of his - <hi>Phyloſophos tantùm extuli, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm impios non oportuit,</hi> - hee recants in the firſt of his Retractations;<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and againſt the <hi>Academicks</hi> hee is at once zealous and peremptorie. - <hi>Hujus mundi Philoſophiam ſacra noſtra meritiſſimè detest antur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> - Our ſacred Diſcipline vtterly deteſts Philoſophie; But what? <hi>The Philoſophie of this world,</hi> which I know not whether it hath more conuinced, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten errour, or improued vs in our knowledge, or ſtaggered vs.<note place="margin">In Col. cum Trypho Indaes.</note> And therefore <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> after his Conuerſion from the Philoſopher to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, complayned hee was deluded by reading <hi>Plato;</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> reports of <hi>Carpocrates</hi> and <hi>Epiphanes,</hi> who reading in PLATOES <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> that - <hi>Wiues ought to bee common,</hi> taught inſtantly their owne to follow that vertuous princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is <hi>Baronius</hi> Quotat.<note place="margin">Ad Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>120.</hi>
               </note> in his 2. Tome, pag. 76. Thus the Gold which SALOMON tranſports from <hi>Ophyr,</hi> hammered and poliſhed as it ought, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Temple, but if it fall into the hands of the <hi>Babilonians</hi> they worke it to the Ruine of the Citie of GOD.</p>
            <p>And by this time PAVL hath paſt his encounter, and begins now to ſuſpect the cenſure of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher. Hee that enters the <hi>Synagogue</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> is to expect nimble Eares, and ſharpe Tongues. If hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25625:11"/>Diſpute, hee muſt hazard an abſurditie; if he Preach, hee <hi>Babbles.</hi> What hee doth on the one ſide leſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectedly, and plaine, the <hi>Epicure</hi> wreſts inſtantly to the cenſure of a <hi>Bull,</hi> what more tierſely, and polite; on the other, the <hi>Stoicke</hi> to a <hi>ſtrong Line.</hi> Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the acuteneſſe of the one, and the ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the other, PAVL ſhall not ſcape his laſh; but the comfort is except that the Paralell (heere) exceeds the patterne, our Criticks are not number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; onely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> - <hi>ſome ſayd;</hi> and theſe ſome (too) very probably, but <hi>Philoſophers;</hi> that is, - <hi>Gloriae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimalia &amp; popularis aurae at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rumoris venalia manoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> as HIEROME characters them. Creatures that will bee bought and ſold for popular applauſe; and when thoſe factions are thus met, that is the iſſue? All they leaue behind is but a meere <hi>ſaying.</hi> - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. - <hi>ſome ſayd,</hi> - and not ſaid onely of late, but done too, done violently againſt PAVL, not onely at <hi>Athens,</hi> in the <hi>Synagogue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17. v. 22.</note> but in the hill of <hi>Mars</hi> too, the place of their conſultation, where if the rude <hi>Epicure</hi> and the <hi>Stoicke</hi> cannot cry him downe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, at <hi>Corinth, Iewes</hi> ſhall riſe againſt him, and bring him to the judgement ſeate before <hi>Gallio</hi> the chiefe Deputie, <hi>for doing things otherwiſe then the Law;</hi> but maugre all their ſpight, it was found (ſaid the Text) out a - <hi>cauill of names and wordes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.5.</note> - and hee is diſmiſt the Tribunall with conſent of the judge, and little glory to the Porſecutor; The ſtory you may finde in the 18. of this Booke, the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neerer home, thus. There is an out-ſide au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie which lookes grim vpon offencos; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſtrangely to publique Reformation; but the heart is double, and the deſigne baſe, when it is not out of zeale to the common cauſe, but enuy to the perſon. There are ſome which can harbour cleanly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25625:12"/>an inueterate grudge, and like cunning Apothecaries guild handſomely their bitter Pills; but when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Reuenge is offred, like Wind that is crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cauernes of the earth, it ſwells and ſtruggles, and ſhakes the whole maſſe and bulke till it hath vent, which not finding cloſe enough by their owne perſons, they ſet their Pioners a digging, and their Moles are heauing vnder earth, thinking to blow vp all vnſeene. There is no malice ſo deſperate as that which lyes in ambuſh, and with her fangs hid, that proiect is euer mercileſſe, though the ſtroake miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie.</p>
            <p>Beloued, if <hi>Athens</hi> bee thus an enemy to <hi>Athens,</hi> and will nurſe vp Snakes in her owne boſome, and vultures for her owne heart, what can ſhee expect from the lippes of Aſpes, and venome of ſharpe ſet Tongues, which cry of her as they did ſometimes of <hi>Ieruſalem, Downe with it euen to the ground? - The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin, daughter is become an Harlot,</hi> the rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouz of the <hi>Epicure,</hi> the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of Lewdneſſe, <hi>the Pappe of exorbitancie,</hi> - <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, - <hi>Some ſayd it.</hi> Some, that not onely went out from vs, but were of vs too, but whileſt heere little better, then profeſſ <hi>Epicures,</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> (lately) bold <hi>Stoickes,</hi> and in a beardleſſe auſteritie, cry downe the Diſcipline of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> in open Senate; There are ſome ſo ambitious of the thing called <hi>Honour,</hi> (indeed but a meere tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and ayre of true Honour) that they will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it through the jawes of Periurie, forgetting the loyaltie they owed to their ſometimes Mother, and the fearefull engagements made her by way of Oath for the vindicating of her honour; but theſe haue <hi>ſayd,</hi> and had they ſaid truely, it had beene in ſuch a high iniuſtice, and in ſonnes too broadly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couers their little truth of affection, and leſſe of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25625:12"/>iudgement. As for thoſe ignorant cryes, the monſter multitude caſts vpon <hi>Athens,</hi> heere, ſhee hath made the obiect both of their ſcorne, and pitie. The wounds, the vnnaturall wounds from her owne NERO ſo touch our AGRIPPINA.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Epicure,</hi> and the <hi>Stoicke, haue ſayd, ſayd;</hi> and done what they can, againſt PAVL, and againſt <hi>Athens;</hi> you haue heard their violence; pleaſe you now turne your attentions from the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> to the <hi>Diuine,</hi> and heare - <hi>What the Babler will ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What will this Babler ſay?</head>
               <p>A GOD at <hi>Mylcium?</hi> at <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> MER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVRIE?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pars</hi> 2. Act 28. verſ. 6. &amp; Cap. 24.12.</note> and at <hi>Athens,</hi> a <hi>Babler?</hi> Sure mens cenſures vary with the place, and as the Clime is ſeated, ſo is the opinion: Had they ſteept all their malice and wit in one head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, and vented it by a tongue more ſcurrilous then that of RABSHEKEY, they could not haue propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the honour of an Apoſtle with a terme of ſuch barbarouſneſſe and derogation. <hi>Babler;</hi> A word ſo foule and odious, of that latitude, and various ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the originall, that both Tranſlators, and Expoſitors,<note place="margin">H ſichias - <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> - Leonardus Arc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus. Beza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n locum, Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us lectio.</note> haue beene plunged ſtrangely and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the apt rendring it in a ſecond Language; to omit the vulgar ones of - <hi>Nugator, Rabula, Gaerris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Blaterator,</hi> - as of thoſe which follow the heele and tracke of the Letter, meerely; others, which more cloſely purſue the Metaphor giue it vs, by - <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minator - verborum,</hi> - a ſower of words;<note place="margin">Eraſmus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> others - <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> - verbius</hi> - a ſeeder of them, a third ſort, - <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niligus,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25625:13"/>- a gatherer of ſeedes, - and this latter ſeemes to Kiſſe and affie neareſt with the nature of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Caietanin lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> an <hi>Atticke</hi> one, (ſayes <hi>Caejetan</hi>) metophorically applyed (heere) and hath reference to thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> certayne Birds (<hi>Aretius</hi> tells vs) ſo called,<note place="margin">Aretius in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> - <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> - from gathering of Seedes, or - <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> - from ſowing of Speeches, - though this latter deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation affect not ſome, as doubly <hi>peccant,</hi> in the Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the Metaphor; for then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> had beene more genuine,<note place="margin">Beza vt ſupra.</note> ſo <hi>Beza.</hi> Birds they were of vile eſteeme amongſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> vſeleſſe, neyther for food, nor ſong, - <hi>Sed garritu perpetuo laborantes,</hi> - ſo continually Chattering, that they did racke and perplexe the eares of all that heard them, inſomuch that it grew prouerbiall amongſt the <hi>Atticks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athanaeus cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab Eraſmo in locum.</note> that hee that was loude in his diſcourſe, or impertinent or profuſe, was inſtantly - <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſeemes to ſound one with that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Athanaeus</hi> touches, - <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> - quoted by <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> The firſt (for ought I reade) that euer made vſe of the word in this diſgracefull way was <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aretius &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmo in locum.</note> and hee flung it vpon <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> who being an <hi>Athenian,</hi> dropt it (be like) afterwards amongſt ſome of the Philoſophers, and a <hi>Stoicke</hi> takes it vppe and beſtowes it heere on an Apoſtle. It was well ſhoulder'd from the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> to the <hi>Diuine;</hi> but, me thinkes it ſhould not ſticke there. <hi>Babling</hi> ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the lippes of the <hi>Leuite;</hi> and it cannot hang truely vpon that tongue which hath beene toucht with a Coale from the Altar; and ſure juſtice can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put it on vs, it muſt bee malice, or preiudice, or both, and both haue done it, not onely on vs, but that great Apoſtle PAVL himſelfe, though choyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verſt in all wayes of Learning, a knowne Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25625:13"/>a profeſſ Diſputant, a great Doctor of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> brought vp at the feet of <hi>Gamaliell,</hi> one that had done ſo many Myracles to the Conuerſion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, aſtoniſhment of all, yet hee cannot paſſe an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian;</hi> without his laſh, a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> without his Quip, - where the Gowne is ſo frequent hard baul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Cryticke; <hi>Lyuie</hi> will not like <hi>Trogus,</hi> nor <hi>Caligula, Lyuie; Athanaeus, Plato,</hi> or a third <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus; Tully; Demoſthenes,</hi> or the <hi>Lypſian, Tully;</hi> ſo many fancies, ſo many cenſures, - no auoyding them at <hi>Athens.</hi> Nay, were PAVL a ſecond time to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue it, hee might yet perchance meete with an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure</hi> or a <hi>Stoicke,</hi> would haue a fling at him with his <hi>Quid vult Seminilegus iste? What will this Babler ſay?</hi> And this Venome towards PAVL ſwells not onely at <hi>Athens,</hi> but at <hi>Dirbe,</hi> and <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> and the chiefe Cities of <hi>Lycaonia;</hi> ſcarce one in a Kingdome but would jerke at a <hi>Paul;</hi> and if hee chance to come before <hi>Foelix</hi> the Gouernour, ſome black mouthed <hi>Tertullus</hi> will bee bawling at the barre ready bill'd with a falſe accuſation,<note place="margin">Act. 24.5.</note> - <hi>This man is a mouer of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, goes about to pollute the Temple, a chiefe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayner of the Sect of the Nazarites.</hi> - Thus ſecular malice (through all ages) hath oppoſed the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, and if it cannot diſparage the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their title, it will ſpitefully plot the traduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their honour. - <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p thou Baldpate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Vp thou Baldpate,</hi> Children can cry at <hi>Bethell;</hi> - and, Hee is factious, hee is vnconformable, hee is a <hi>Babler,</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> is the popular and common <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ogue.</hi> Heere is a large Field offered me through which I might trauell, but this is not my way, it is too trodden; euery Hackney rodes it, I haue found out as neere a cut, though the paſſage may ſeeme more ſtony and vneuen; thither bend I, where I ſhall ſhew you,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25625:14"/>how in Diuine matters wee may bee ſaid to <hi>Babble?</hi> how in Secular? in eyther how not? The <hi>Symptomes</hi> of that <hi>Lip - diſeaſe,</hi> the danger, the judgement on it, the cure. Let the <hi>Epicure,</hi> and the <hi>Stoicke,</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while) lay by their cenſure, and heare, now - <hi>What this Babler will ſay?</hi> -</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Speech</hi> is the very image whereby the Mind and Soule of the ſpeaker conueyeth it ſelfe into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of him that heareth.<note place="margin">Heoker, lib. <hi>5.</hi> Eccleſ. Pol.</note> The Sterne and Rother of the Soule which diſpoſeth the hearts and affections of men,<note place="margin">Charron, lib. <hi>3.</hi> Wiſedome.</note> like certayne notes to make vp, an exact har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. But this muſt bee ſort and gentle then, not ouerſcrued; It is with Speech, as it is with Tunes, if keyed too high, racke no leſſe the Inſtrument then the eare that heares them, when thoſe which are lower pitcht make the harmony both full, and ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; your tumid and forced language harrowes the attention, when the facill and flowing ſtile doth not ſo much inuite applauſe, as command it; it is a gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but an emaſculate and weake eloquence, which is dreſt onely in a pompe of wordes, and glories more in the ſtrength of the <hi>Epythet,</hi> then the matter; this is the <hi>Body,</hi> the other but the <hi>Garment</hi> of our diſcourſe, which wee ſhould ſuite as well to euery ſubiect, as occaſion; ſometimes more liberally, ſometimes more contractedly, leaſt wee be ſaid to <hi>Babble,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heccatus.</note> - for it is true what <hi>Archidamus</hi> told the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator of old, - They which know how to ſpeake well, know alſo their times of ſilence. - And (indeed) to ſpeake appoſitely and much, is not the part of one man,<note place="margin">Eccluſ. 21.25.</note> I am ſure, not of a wiſe man. - <hi>The wordes of him which hath vnderſtanding, are weighed in the ballance.</hi> - Marke - weighed, in the Ballance. - Heere is deliberation of ſpeech, euenneſſe - <hi>Pone Domine cuſtodiam ort meo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 141.3.</note> - was the Prayer of <hi>Daeuid,</hi> - ſet a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25625:14"/>watch before my lippes. And in the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Veſſell that had not the couering faſtened to it was vncleane; and therefore the inner-Parts of a Foole are reſembled to a broken veſſell, which hath neyther part entire, nor couering, Hee can keepe no knowledge while hee liueth, <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 21.14.<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thoſe more nobly bred amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned firſt to hold their peace, and afterwards to ſpeake.<note place="margin">De <hi>3.</hi> plici Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: ling. man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment.</note> - For <hi>Vnde illi cura Cordis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>cui ne ipſa quidèm adhùc oris circumſpectio?</hi> Hee is an ill treaſurer of his owne thoughts, that keepes not the doores of his lippes ſhut; and that heart is neuer lockt faſt vpon any ſecret, where a profuſe tongue layes intereſt to the Key.</p>
               <p>And therefore, Nature hath prouided well by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying this member more then any part of the <hi>Body,</hi> ſetting a garriſon of the ſtrong and ſtout men about it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. doubly intrenching it with lippes and teeth, not ſo much to oppoſe a forraine inuaſion as to allay mutinies within, for the tongue is an vnruely member; and ſides much with the peruerſneſſe of our will; and therefore Reaſon ſhould keepe ſtrict ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell vpon it, and as well direct, as guard it. Nature hath proportioned vs a double Eare and Eye to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Tongue, and Reaſon interprets inſtantly - <hi>Wee ſhould heare and ſee twice, ere wee ſpeake once.</hi> And indeed our Tongues would follow our ſence (ſayes <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) and not our will,<note place="margin">Ad Fratres in Erem. ſerm. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and the Father puts the Foole handſomely vpon him, - <hi>Qui non priùs verbum ducit ad linguam rationis, quàm educat ad linguam oris.</hi> -</p>
               <p>Let Reaſon (ſaith the Sonne of <hi>Syrach</hi>) goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery enterprize and counſaile to euery Action,<note place="margin">Eccluſ. 37.16.</note> - to euery vertuous action, (beſides the latter of theſe) the Philoſopher allowes a double Aduerbe, - <hi>Scientèr,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſtoil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Elluc. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25625:15"/>
                  <hi>Conſtantèr.</hi> - So that euery diſcreet deſigne muſt haue beſides Reaſon, Knowledge, Counſaile, Conſtancy; Reaſon and Knowledge, the pole and card to direct it; Counſaile, Conſtancie, to ſteere and ballace it. Hence it is that the tongue of a Wiſe man is in his heart,<note place="margin">Eccluſ. 21.</note> and where the heart of a Foole is, no igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſo womaniſh but tels you.</p>
               <p>So that the obſeruation of S. <hi>Bernard</hi> comes ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably heere,<note place="margin">Bernard vt ſup.</note> - <hi>Non perſonam tibi velim ſuſpectam eſſe, ſed linguam, praeſertim in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn ocinatione com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni,</hi> - In common talke wee are not to heed the perſon ſo much as the tongue, for by the <hi>babling</hi> of that wee may roue at the weight or weakneſſe of the Maſter; for commonly hee that nothing but talkes, talkes nothing, nothing of bulke or ſubſtance, ſhells onely and barkes of things without their pith or kernell.</p>
               <p>To auoyd then this diſeaſe of <hi>Babling</hi> and profuſe emptying of vaine words,<note place="margin">Marke, 9.</note> the Diſciples were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, - their - <hi>Habete Sal in vobis;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit 12.13. Coloſ. 4.6.</note> - and Salt (you know) was commanded of old, not only to Men, but to <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Words.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Fratres in Erem. ſerm. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> That to words (not ſauoured aright) S. <hi>Augustine</hi> calls, - <hi>Sal infatuatum ad nullum condimentum,</hi> - it ſeaſons nothing as it ſhould doe, euery thing reliſhes amiſſe it toucheth. For the <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> doth not meaſure words by their weight, but by their number, neyther regards hee what he ſpeakes, but how much; Thus whiles he labours to perſwade the eare, hee wounds it, and to inuite his hearer, he torments him. In the Leuiticall Law, the man that had - <hi>Fluxum ſemims,</hi> - was vncleane; - And <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> turnes the Allegorie, on the diſpencers of holy Myſteries. - GODS Word is the Seed, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher the Sower of it;<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. ſeminat.</note> or, as <hi>The</hi> Father hath it on the Parable, - <hi>Cophinus ſeminantis,</hi> - the Seedeſmans
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25625:15"/>basket. - If hee bee then - <hi>Jncaeutè loquax,</hi> - vnpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditately <hi>babling. - Non ad vſum generis, ſed ad immunditiam ſemen effundit,</hi> - and ſuch a one in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue times was called - <hi>Semini - verbius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg lib. <hi>2.</hi> Paſt. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> - the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tels vs in the 2. part of his <hi>Paſtorals,</hi> 4. Chapter. And no doubt hee that ſowes ouermuch by the Tongue ſhall ſeldome fructifie, except the ſeed bee choice and orderly diſpoſed,<note place="margin">Charron. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Speech being <hi>the more exquiſite communication of Diſcourſe and Reaſon,</hi> which as it ſhould not bee too courſely open, ſo not inuolued;<note place="margin">Themiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocles. -</note> Hence the <hi>Athenian</hi> compared it to a rich piece of Arras drawne out in varietie of Stories, which diſplayed, opened both delight and wonder, but folded vp, neyther; For, it is with Speech as with ſome Aromaticks and perfumes, which in the maſſe and role ſmell little, but beaten abroad fill the roome with fragancy. Matter wound vp in obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of language growes to the nature of a Riddle, and is not ſo properly Speech, as Myſterie; Things that hammer onely on our eares, not our interlectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, are no more words, but ſounds, meere - <hi>babling</hi> - ayre (onely,) beaten with diſtinctleſſe and confuſed noyſe, nothing of ſubſtance in it for matter, or for forme; And the man that affects ſuch marticulate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, heare how <hi>Gregory</hi> playes vpon,<note place="margin">Nazian. in Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol.</note> - <hi>Ego ſolertiae nomine admiror, ne dicam, ſtultitiae.</hi> A Wiſe man (ſayes the Philoſopher of old) when hee openeth his lippes,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> as in a Temple wee Behold the goodly ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes and images of the Soule, - And indeed that Eloquence that is made the obiect of our ſence, and intellectuals carries with it both maieſtie and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when that which runnes in a myſt or vayle, Cenſure for the moſt part, ſometimes, Pitie. Let the <hi>Babler</hi> then that thus ſpeakes in a Cloud, - <hi>Pray that hee may interpret,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.13.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.13.</note> it will require a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25625:16"/>Comment from his owne induſtry; others, are too dull to vndertake a taske of ſuch an endleſſe trauaile. It is a prepoſterous way of interpretation, when the gloſſe growes obſcurer then the Text; Sermons which were firſt intended for the illumination of the vnderſtanding, are at length growne like thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres of the Oracles, both intricate and doubtfull, They will require the heate of a ſublimated braine, eyther to apprehend their raptures, or to reconcile them. But why at <hi>Athens</hi> ſuch prodigies of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? Such monſters of affectation? Why this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laborate vanitie? This induſtrious <hi>Babling?</hi> Let it no more touch the grauitie of the <hi>Typpet,</hi> or the <hi>Scarlet,</hi> as fitter for a Deske then a Pulpit, and a laſh, then a reproofe. But, ſoft <hi>Stoicke.</hi> Let me not bee cenſured heere too haſtily a <hi>Babler.</hi> I am not ſo much a friend to the ſlouenly diſcourſe, as to loath that which hath a decent and modeſt dreſſe; wordes apt and choyſe, I hate not, onely thoſe tortured, and affected ones; I preferre S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> golden Key before his wooden, though this may vnlocke Myſteries as well as that; yet would I not giue way to the kick-ſhawed diſcourſe, where there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more ſauce then meate; or, as <hi>Quintillian</hi> ſpake of <hi>Seneca, - Chalke without Sand,</hi> - more of luſtre then of weight; It is the well wouen and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall piece taskes mee, yet that too, not without the flouriſhings and intermixtures of diſcreet lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. For it is heere as it is in Needle-workes, where wee allow light colours, ſo the ground bee ſadde. The Breſtplate of Iudgement which <hi>Aaron</hi> wore was made with embroydered workes,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.15.</note> and in the Ephod, there were as well diuerſities of colours as of riches, - Blew ſilke, and Purple, and Scarlet, and fine Linnen. - That then of <hi>Epiphamus</hi> is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25625:16"/>thy both of your memory and imitation, - whoſe workes were read of the ſimple for the wordes, of the Learned for the matter. - So, - hee that will not runne the cenſure of a <hi>Babler,</hi> muſt haue as well his deepes for the Elephant, as his ſhallowes for the Lambe; Knowing that ſome are tranſported with heate of fancy, and others with ſtrength of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and it is in the choyce of eyther, as in that of Stuffes, which ſome buy for the roundneſſe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the threed, others for the lightneſſe of the colour. Matter not cloathed in handſomeneſſe of wordes is but duſted treaſure, and like ſome Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens where there is fatneſſe of earth, no Flower. Your embelliſht phraſe without ſollidneſſe of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but - <hi>Copioſa aegestas</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſtiles it) a gaudie pouertie, and like ſome vnhappy Tilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, where there is more of Poppie and Darnell, then good Corne; But, where the materials are cleane, the language keem'd, there is the workmanſhip of an exact Pen-man; If they are both well mixt and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, there is a choyce maſter-piece, <hi>Apelles</hi> himſelfe hath beene there.</p>
               <p>And howeuer, the diſcourſe that is ſo bruſht and ſwept others haue thought too effeminate for the Pulpit, yet, in ſome it is no way of affectation, but of knowledge. High fancies cannot creepe to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expreſſions, and the fault is oftentimes in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice or weakeneſſe of the receiuer, not in the ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borateneſſe of the Pen-man. Sermons are not to bee meaſured by their ſound, or the haſte and vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of a dull organ, the Eare is a deceitfull one, full of winding and vncertayne doores, and often carries falſe meſſages to the Sence, the Eye as it is a more ſubtle organ, ſo a more certayne, and though that bee ſometimes deceiued too when it is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25625:17"/>of the diſtance, yet vpon ſtricter peruſall of the obiect, it giues you vncorrupt intelligence, when wordes paſſe (for the moſt part) by our cares like tunes in a double conſort, which wee may heare, not diſtinguiſh.</p>
               <p>And yet notwithſtanding, though at <hi>Athens</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Philoſophers, this polite way of diſcourſe may bee paſſable, and draw on ſometimes approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſometimes applauſe; yet at <hi>Epheſus</hi> (where PAVL is to encounter Beaſts) it is but meere <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 26.13.</note> And to what purpoſe thoſe loftie varieties, in ſprinkled Congregations? Raptures and high viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are for <hi>Ceſarea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 28.14.</note> when PAVL is to ſpeake before <hi>Agrippa,</hi> thinner exhortations will ſerue the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at <hi>Putcoli.</hi> - And when all thoſe deſcants and quauerings of the plauſible and harmonious tongue ſhall looſe their volubilitie and ſweetneſſe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to warble (as the time will come (the Preacher tels vs) <hi>when all thoſe Daughters of Muſicke ſhall bee brought low</hi>) the plaine ſong muſt take at laſt,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> that which is ſet to euery capacitie and eare; and yet will affoord you, as well her varieties of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as delight; to the judicious ſollid fluentneſſe, to apprehenſions lower-roofed wayes more troden to aduiſe, and comfort; to the weake and Soule-ſicke, the ſtill voyce, to the obſtinate, and remorſeleſſe, <hi>lowder ſounds;</hi> perchance this thunderclap may breed a ſhower, that ſhower, a ſun ſhine. Teares and Comfort are the ſucciſſory children of reprehenſion, ſometimes, the twinnes; Let the ſword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit then cut both wayes, but more to reproofe, then menacing; maſter thy Vineger with Oyle, ſo thou ſhall not ſo much ſharpen the heart of the Sinner, as ſupple it; ſome grow more refractary by rebuke, and ſome more ſlexible; For, it is with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25625:17"/>the word of a Preacher, as it is with Fire, which both molliſies and hardens <hi>Steele,</hi> according to the varietie of heates. If wee deriue onely from one Throne coles of fire, and hot Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts, wee kindle diſpaire in him wee teach, not reformation; It is the temperate and gentle fire ſparkles into zeale, when that which is too high and turbulent growes at an inſtant both flame and aſhes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Let the Righteous ſmite mee friendly</hi> (ſayes the Kingly Prophet) <hi>but let not their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious balmes breake my head.</hi> - I allow repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion a Rod, but not a Fleyle, a hand to laſh the tranſgreſſions of the time, not as ſome doe to threſh them.</p>
               <p>PAVL will preſcribe the Spirituall combatant a Sword, but not a Speare;<note place="margin">Achillis.</note> except hee had the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> - which would both wound and cure. <hi>Marah</hi> may haue bitter waters, but <hi>Gilead</hi> muſt haue balme too for the broken heart. Where ſinnes are full kern'd and ripe, I deny not a Sickle to cut them downe, but the ſinner, whither as Corne for the Barne, or Chaffe for the fire, I leaue to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the great Harueſtman.</p>
               <p>In the apparition of GOD to <hi>Eliah,</hi> on Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> (you know the Text,<note place="margin">1. King. 19.11.12.</note> and therefore gueſſe at the alluſion.) A ſtrong winde rent the Mountaines, and brake in pieces the Rocke, before the Lord; but the Lord was not in it, and there was a great Earthquake and a Fire, but the Lord was not in it. And in thoſe windes and fires, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes which are both ſeene and heard on our <hi>Horeb</hi> heere, the Lord oftentimes is not in them, for then the mountainous and rockie heart would bee cleft a ſunder, now it is vnbattered and rib'd with Adamant proofe againſt perſwaſion,</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:25625:18"/>
               <p> Knowing that theſe are but <hi>Men</hi> of Thunder, counterfeit thunder too, and there is a GOD that rules the true, his hot bolts and coles of Fire they quake and tremble at, not thoſe fire-workes, and ſquibs, and flaſhes heere below, which ſpleenaticke men fling about (as they thinke) to terrour, but they returne by ſcorne.<note place="margin">Bernard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lod.</note> It is true (ſayes <hi>Bernard</hi>) - <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo est Ventus,</hi> but it is not alwayes, - <hi>Ventus vrens,</hi> - <hi>ſurge Aquilo, veni Auſter, perfla hortum meum, &amp; ſluant Aramata illius,</hi> - Ariſe O North, and come O South (the one (you know) is moyſt, and the other cold) yet both of theſe muſt blow on the garden of the Spouſe, that the Spices thereof may flow out,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.6. In the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> did not Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine drop as the raine? and Speech ſtill as dew? as the ſhower vpon Hearbes? and as the great raine vpon the Graſſe?<note place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> I confeſſe, on <hi>Synay</hi> once there was a thicke Cloud, Lightning and Thunder, and the mountayne ſmoaked;<note place="margin">Exod. 20.18.</note> but the Text ſayes, - <hi>The people fledde from it.</hi> - But on mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> the Cloud was bright, the Sunne cleere, and a Voyce heard in ſtead of Thunder, and then the Diſciples cry, - <hi>Edificemus Domine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 17.2.4, 5.</note> - Let vs build heere.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the numberleſſe Gods the Heathens had, and the diuers wayes of Sacrifice they appeaſed them with, the Romaines had their - <hi>Hoſtiam Animalem,</hi> - in which the Soule onely was conſecrated to GOD, - the Hoſt they offered muſt bee pure and choyſe, not of Bulls or Swine, as creatures fierce and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, but of Kids and Lambes, more innocent and milde, and of theſe too, ſuch as were not lame, or diſeaſed, or had - <hi>Caudam aculeatam,</hi> or, - <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guammgram,</hi> - ſayes my Antiquary.<note place="margin">Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> You ſee ſtings in the tayle, and blackneſſe in tongue are exempted heere and thought vnfit for this ſacrifice of the Soule.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:25625:18"/>
               <p> Let the virulent <hi>Babler</hi> leaue the Letter and take the Allegorie, and hee hath applyed; - For venemous and foule language doth exaſperate and obdure euen thoſe which the modeſt and gentle pierces. Let Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes beate againſt a Rocke, they fall backe without wounding it, yet if moderate and gentle drops fall on a Stone they hollow it, not by violence,<note place="margin">Jn Praefat. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</note> but the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Diſtillation. Sheepe (ſayes <hi>Nazianzene</hi>) are not to bee gouerned by rigour, but perſwaſion; all thoſe impulſions of neceſſitie and force, carry with them a ſhew of tyrannie, and hold neyther with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor obſeruation,<note place="margin">Idem Ibid.</note> - <hi>Non ſecùs ac planta per vim manibus inflexa,</hi> - ſayes the Father. Bend a Plant (and it is with moſt men as it is with plants) it turnes againe. There was neuer diſpoſition, not cowardly and baſe, that violence could worke vpon. Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie if it bee not alwayes voluntary, it may bee ledde ſometimes, but neuer drawne; And therefore <hi>Peter</hi> feeds his Flocke, not by conſtraint, but willingly, and (as your common <hi>Bablers</hi> neuer doe) <hi>not for filtby Lucre, but a ready minde.</hi> 1. <hi>Peter,</hi> 5.2.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2.</note> And indeed it is this <hi>filthy-Lucre</hi> - hath occaſioned ſo many <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> in our Church, thoſe that will ſay any thing for the inhauncement of their profite, the improuing of their Stipend; Brey at Vniuerſities for a morſell of bread; giue blowes againſt Learning, make ſcarres in the face of Knowledge, cry downe the vſe of Arts, or what is curiouſly ſtrung in ſecular Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, abandon them from the ſippes of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and confine him onely to a ſacred dialect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermixture of prophane Knowledge, or ſleeke of humane Eloquence; No marrow of the Father, no ſubtilty of the Schoole-man, no grauitie of the Philoſopher, no policie of the Hiſtorian; thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing the Church of varietie of Guifts, and mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25625:19"/>and pinning the Holy Ghoſt to a defect of all outward ornaments, as if that winde which bloweth where it liſt were forbad to breath any where but in their new-fangled and braine-ſicke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that the diſtribution of holy Myſteries growes ſo to contempt, the diſpencers of them enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled to tearmes of obloquy and ſcorne, expoſed to the Paraphraſe and Comment of the jeering aduerſary. Our <hi>Athens</hi> diſparaged, Learning of no price and value, Preaching, <hi>Babling,</hi> and the mayne reaſon and inducement why the whole body of Arts thus reeles and wauers. I haue at length met the <hi>Babler,</hi> I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to grapple with, and wee muſt exchange a few blowes ere wee part, in which I ſhall bee home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much floriſh. <hi>Stoicke,</hi> once more forbeare. Stand aloofe till wee haue paſt <hi>this</hi> Duell, then let thy cenſure fall, as the wounds doe, luſtly. Suppoſe we then a man harneſſed and clad with all the glories and habiliments of Nature, beſides the rich dowrie and treaſure of Art and Knowledge, yet ſay I not that <hi>this</hi> man without a ſupernaturall light from the Scripture, is able to vtter thoſe Myſteries as hee ought, eyther in their ſtrength, or decencie. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the beſt of ours, eyther for depth of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or ſublimitie of Inuention, or accurateneſſe of Compoſure, or cleanneſſe of Zeale, are comparatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meere <hi>Bablings,</hi> and fall many bowes ſhort of thoſe inſpired ones of old; neyther are they Gods word (ſayes <hi>Hooker</hi>) in the ſame manner that the Sermons of the Prophets were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> b. <hi>5.</hi> Eccliſt. Polit.</note> no they are ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly tearmed his Word,<note place="margin">Doct. Cowels Defence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he Chapter of Preaching.</note> and are no more the ſame, then is the Diſcourſe the Theame, or the Line the Rule, by which it is drawne; yet haue they a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity both of vertue and ſucceſſe; ſtrange preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25625:19"/>ouer the ſodaine paſſions and affections of moſt men, whom they not leade onely but entangle, and not fetter barely, but entraunce; in a word, they raigne ouer vs and eſtabliſh a violent empire and command ouer our very Soules. Diuinitie we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſoueraigne Lady and Queene of all Sciences, Arts (if you approue the ſtile) her Maydes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Are wee not ſacriligious then to the ſtate of Soueraigntie when wee rob it of her trayne? The chiefeſt complement of Greatneſſe is the retinue, take away her equipage you diſnoble it. Barre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Learning of the attendance of that which is ſecular, Arts, Sciences, you diſrobe it, ſtrip it of its glory.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Diuinity</hi> (ſaith <hi>Baſilly</hi> is the fruit, Arts as the leaues, and leaues are not onely for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament but ſuccour.</note> Certaine truths in her cannot fully bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered without ſome meaſure of Knowledge in them all. The Axiomes and principles of Humanitie though they a little runne by thoſe of Diuinitie, yet they doe not thwart them, there may bee difference, no contrarietie, no not in thoſe things which ſeeme to carry a ſhew of contrariety. Reaſon our Miſtreſſe tels vs, - <hi>Verum vero conſonat,</hi> - and Truth ſtands di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically oppoſed to Falſhood, not to a ſecond truth; for - <hi>Vero nil verius,</hi> - Philoſophicall truths challenge the ſame ſowrce and pedigree Theologicall doe, the ſame fountaine, and Father, GOD, and are of the like Truth, though not of the like Authority.</p>
               <p>Hence flowes that admirable conſent and harmony between the naturall patefactions of GOD, and the ſupernaturall;<note place="margin">Amand. Polan. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Logic. fol. <hi>213.</hi>
                  </note> for from God is both Reaſon and Scripture, and Reaſon being obſcured by Sinne, and blemiſhed by her many errours, the Scripture doth vnſcale and beames againe, and ſo ſets her free from her former obliquities and digreſſions,<note place="margin">De Fugaſaeculi. Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> the light of Nature being dimmed (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) was to bee cleared by the Law, the wreſts of the Law by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25625:20"/>
                  <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſo that Grace doth not aboliſh Nature, but perfect it,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in <hi>Haſ. 101.</hi>
                  </note> neyther doth Nature reject Grace (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) but imbrace it. Nay, my Author (and I haue gleaned I confeſſe ſome few eares of Corne from his more plentifull crop) quotes <hi>Tertullian</hi> too very appoſitely,<note place="margin">Theolog. Logic. pag <hi>200.</hi>
                  </note> (and 'tis like <hi>Tertullians</hi> both for the marrow and the reach.) - God firſt ſent Nature to bee our Schoolemiſtreſſe, being after to ſend Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that thou being firſt the Diſciple of Nature, mighteſt afterwards the more eaſily bee induced to beleeue Propheſie. Wee may not thinke then the <hi>Ipſe Dixit</hi> of the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or the weighty depoſitions of prophane Authors, to bee meere <hi>Chimaeraes,</hi> fruitleſſe Fancies, <hi>Bablings</hi> of no conſequence; though ſome of them were not true Viſions, yet they were not all ſtarke Dreames, PAVL then would neuer haue confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Idolaters of <hi>Athens</hi> with their owne * Text,<note place="margin">Act 17.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> - <hi>Some of your owne Poets haue ſayd it;</hi> There may bee much Hay and Stubble amongſt them, but there is ſome Gold, and precious Stones; try them, if they indure not the touch, throw them by as mettals too courſe and droſſie; but if there be rich Oare mixt with veynes of Earth, why not ſeparated? Why not purged by the fire of Gods word? Why may not this ſtranger to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> her head ſhauen, and the haire of her eye-browes cut bee admitted into the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary? If one <hi>Copernicus</hi> bee troubled with the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigo, and would haue the earth runne round as his head does, ſhall a whole Sect of <hi>Ariſtotelians</hi> bee lyable to a diſeaſe of giddineſſe? Though a <hi>Stoicke</hi> or an <hi>Epicure</hi> oppoſe PAVL, yet at <hi>Athens</hi> there were <hi>Academickes,</hi> and <hi>Peripatetickes,</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers too, without their tumult, and for ought the Text caueat's mee to the contrary, they were his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25625:20"/>Conuerts too. And it is euident that the Apoſtles, and after them the Fathers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Cowell.</note> made Arts the Chiefe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons againſt the Enemies of the Church, for as ſome opinions would not bee conuinced without humane Learning,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> ſo others affections would not bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded without that eloquence, thus they wounded the Hereſies and Apoſtaſies of their times, when the Reuolted <hi>Iulian</hi> was impelled to ſay:<note place="margin">Greg. Nazian.</note> - <hi>We are ſtrucke through with our owne Darts.</hi> - All Science what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is in the nature of good; and good is good, whereſoeuer I finde it.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. contra Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a withered branch</hi> (ſayes <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to his Donatiſt) <hi>a Grape ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times may hang, ſhall I refuſe the Grape becauſe the ſtaulke is withered?</hi> If on a tempeſtuous ſhore I meete by chance a rich piece of Amber, or richer Pearle, amongſt oare, and ſhels, and froath, and ſands, ſhall I refuſe eyther for the ſtench of the place or the companions? I haue ſeldome read of any thing but a fooliſh Cocke that refuſed Treaſure, though on a dunghill. I know Heathens had their ſlime and mud, and ſome of their ſtreames ranne impurely, yet they had their Chriſtall fountaynes too, eſpecially the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> of which wee might <hi>draw,</hi> and <hi>drinke,</hi> and drinke our fill, and drinke as <hi>our owne,</hi> too, (<hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayes) they being in the tenure of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt poſſeſſors.<note place="margin">Auguſt lib <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> de Doct Chriſh and cap. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> For as the <hi>Iſraclites</hi> (it is the Fathers ſimilitude) tooke from the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> their Idols, and Rings, and ſiluer, &amp; Gold, and beſtowed the ſame vpon the adorning of the Lords Tabernacle, which they had abuſed by pride and ryot, to the beautifying of the Temples of their falſe Gods, and did this - <hi>Non auctoritate propriâ ſed praecepto</hi> (ſayes the Father) not by the inſtigation of their owne will, but by mandat, <hi>ſic Doctrinae omnes Gentilium<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, non ſolum ſimulata &amp; ſuperſtitioſe figmema, &amp;c.</hi> So all thoſe Doctrines of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25625:21"/>the Gentiles (their ſuperſtitious fictions expunged and layd by) their liberall Diſciplines and Precepts of manners (which were their Gold and Siluer) may bee reduced to the vſe of ſacred Learning, and a Chriſtian may challenge them - <hi>Ad vſum juſtum praedicandi Euangelij,</hi> - they are the Fathers owne wordes. - Howeuer hee puts in a caueat by the way - a - <hi>ſed hoc modo inſtructus,</hi> - the Diuine that is thus accommodated when hee ſhall addreſſe himſelfe to the vſe and ſearch of theſe heathen tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>res, <hi>Illud Apoſtolicum cogitare non ceſſet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> - <hi>Scientia inflat, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas aedificat,</hi> - in his <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Doct. Chriſtian.</hi> 40. Cap. I neuer yet read that the true vſe of ſecular Learning tooke from the glory of that which was Diuine, I haue, that it hath added, nor that any thing gleaned and pickt, and culled with a cleane hand was diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto GOD,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Cornel,</note> I haue that it was approued. I know there is a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enomous eloquence</hi> (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote of that of <hi>Nouatus</hi>) and this perchance the <hi>Babler</hi> himſelfe vſes, when hee leades ſilly Creatures captiue, but it is odious both to GOD and Man, and hath beene the maine Engine in all Ages by which <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> haue wrought. In thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of old, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4.5. You know whatſoeuer was vncleane, <hi>was an abominuation vnto the Lord;</hi> the Offering it ſelfe muſt bee without blemiſh, the Altar ſeuen dayes cleanſed before it was layd on, the Prieſt too waſhed before the Congregation, ere hee dared to immolate; and why not ſo in this Holocauſt and Sacrifice of the lippes? Why not the Offering with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemiſh, the Altar cleanſed, the Prieſt ſo in his Diſcourſe too, that what is kindled heere may burne as a ſweet Incenſe vnto the Lord? ſmells that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauoury neuer touch his noſtrils, ſounds harſh and jarring, neuer his eares; and therefore, the Bells of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25625:21"/>
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> were of pure Gold, - <hi>Ne ſubaeratum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod tinniat in Sacerdotio,</hi> - ſaith <hi>Gregory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg Nazian. Apolog.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is a ſullenneſſe, or rather policy, moſt in our age haue got, that what is in a way of eminence and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, they cenſure as a piece of affectation or curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie, when (God knowes) it is but to colour ſome ſiniſter pretence, and for a fairer varniſh of their owne weakneſſes. You know the ſtory of the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the Cocke, and the Boy that kept the liue ones from his ſhop leaſt comming too nigh, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſſe of that hand ſhould bee diſcouered, which had drawne the other at ſo rude a poſture.</p>
               <p>There is a malicious ignorance poſſeſſeth many, by which they vnder-value all things aboue their ſpheare, and cry downe that induſtry or Art in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which is beyond the verge and fathome of their owne abilities. But why ſhould Moles repine that other ſee? Or Cripples murmure that others halt not? <hi>Tolle quod tuùm est &amp; Vade.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom. ad Col. phurnium.</note> Yet loe how euen thoſe laſt and gaſping times keepe vp with the manner of thoſe of old, both in their ſpleene and weakeneſſe. There bee (ſaith the Father to his <hi>Marcellinus</hi>) that account inciuilitie of Manners and rudeneſſe of Speech, true Holineſſe,<note place="margin">Hieronimus.</note> - and with ſuch, - <hi>Quis non <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icus abundat?</hi> Would I could not ſay, - <hi>Quae Academia?</hi> Theſe Cynickes are in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tub, theſe <hi>Stoickes</hi> heere at <hi>Athens.</hi> But why ſhould the talke of ſuch bee a burthen in our way? Learning vnto a Wiſe-man is as an ornament of Gold, and like a bracelet on his Arme,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 21.15.</note> but Fetters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the feete, and Manackles about the hands; of whom? of him that (but now) was the burthen in the way, the <hi>Foole,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 21.21.</note> whom leaſt wee ſhould leaue without his companion, <hi>Syracides</hi> brings home to the gates of the <hi>Babler,</hi> and I will leaue him there,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25625:22"/>- <hi>As a houſe that is deſtroyed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 21.18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo is Learning to a Foole,</hi> and <hi>his Knowledge is but talke without ſence,</hi> Eccluſ. 21.18. the tayle of the Verſe carryeth the ſting; for much of our <hi>Bablers</hi> knowledge is little better then - <hi>Sermo ſine ſenſu,</hi> Wordes without Salt, Speech with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ballace. And yet (good Lord) how theſe lampes burne in our Tabernacles, theſe Bells ſound in our Sanctuary? They are the thunderbolts of our Congregations, the Hotſpurres of our Pulpits. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſinnes of the time they clacke loude, and often, but it is like Mills driuen by a haſty torrent, which grinde much, but not cleane; And indeed it is not much they grinde neyther, in ſubſtance, but in ſhew, neyther is the labour ſo ſuperlatiue, as the noyſe. Some that haue been conuerſant in the trade, ſay, that Corne that is cleane and maſſie, will lye long in the wombe and body of the Mill and requires all the induſtry of ſtone and water, and will not bee deliuered without ſome time and trauaile, when graines which are mixt and courſe, runne through with leſſe difficultie, and more tumult. The <hi>Babler</hi> will apply. Thus wee ſee empty veſſels ſound much, and ſhallow ſtreames runne ſwift and loude, but on barren grounds, when thoſe deeper ones glide ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as with more grauitie, ſo more ſilence, yet on fat ſolves, and ſo the neighbouring Fields grow fertile with their abundance. If all truth of Religion raigned in the Tongue, and the ſubduing of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſold rebellion, in the mortification of the Looke, there were no ſanctitie but here. - But the heate of this mans zeale, is like that of Glaſſe, which will bee blowne into any forme according to the fancy of him that blowes it, ſometimes into that of a Serpent, ſometimes of a Doue, but more often of a Serpent, then of a Doue, not for the wiſedome of it, but the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25625:22"/>venome. Euery word is a ſting againſt the Church, her Diſcipline, truth of Gouernment, Hee <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> ſhrewdly againſt each Inſtitution of it, State, Ceremonies, makes them adulterate, the dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Great whore, and ſets all without the walls of reformation, which Wheele and Role not with the giddineſſe of his tenents. The Golden-mouthed <hi>Homilist</hi> in his fourth vpon the <hi>Acts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> ſpeaking of that miraculous way of the Holy Ghoſts deſcent vpon the Apoſtles in the day of <hi>Penticost,</hi> obſerues nimbly, thus; - There came a ſound from Heauen, - <hi>As it were</hi> - of a Ruſhing and mightie winde, and there appeared to them Clouen tongues, - <hi>As it were</hi> - of Fire, - <hi>Rectè vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> additum est, - <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elut - ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſenſibile de Spiritu ſuſpicareris,</hi> - ſayes the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. - And indeed, in thoſe phanaticke Spirits, though the Tongues bee fiery, and the voyce as the Windes, ruſhing; yet in themſelues there is nothing ſenſible; For as thoſe which appeared to the Apoſtles, were but - <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elut igncae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt Homil. <hi>4.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Act.</hi>
                  </note> - and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elut flatus,</hi> - ſo this orall vehemency is but - <hi>Velut Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and <hi>Velut Indignatio,</hi> - Falſe fire, or, at beſt, but ſome hot exhalation in the braine ſet on fire by continuall motion and agitation of the Tongue, and there it burnes ſometimes to the madneſſe of the Profeſſour, moſt times, of the Diſciple. Againe, theſe Tongues are ſaid to <hi>ſit</hi> vpon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, - <hi>Sedendi verbum ſtabilitatem ac manſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem denotat,</hi> the ſame Father - ſitting preſuppoſes <hi>Stabilitie</hi> and <hi>Manſion,</hi> but moſt of theſe haue neyther, eyther in their opinion, or courſe of life, but as the contribution ebbes or flowes; ſo they hoyſe, or ſtrike ſayle, eyther way, ſometimes for the wide mayne, ſometimes for the next harbour.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25625:23"/>Againe, the Apoſtles are ſayd there, to bee <hi>filled</hi> with the <hi>Holy Ghost. - Rectè repleti, non enim vulgaritèr acciperunt gratiam Spiritus, ſed eoſque vt impleren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> the Father ſtill. - Where the Spirit powres out it leaues no part emptie, it doth fill, fill vp euen to the brim, giues power of ſpeaking roundly, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; where it doth giue power, - no Rhumaticke En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſmes, no languiſhing ejaculations, but ſuch as the Spirit indeed haue dictated, ſuch as flow from lippes immediately touched with the true Cherubin, and a Tongue ſwolne with inſpiration. Againe, the Tongues which ſate vpon the Apoſtles were <hi>clouen Tongues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Geneua</hi> Notes in 2. chap. Acts.</note> other tongues, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. and S. <hi>Marke</hi> calls them <hi>new Tongues.</hi> They were not confined then to a ſingle dialect to <hi>Babling</hi> meerely in our Mother tongue, but the Text ſayes they had diuers Tongues, of the <hi>Parthian,</hi> and <hi>Mede,</hi> and <hi>Elamite, Phrygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and <hi>Pamphilian,</hi> and of thoſe of <hi>Lybia</hi> which is beſide <hi>Cyreue,</hi> And in thoſe and (other Tongues too) they <hi>ſpake the sonderfull workes of God.</hi> Act. 2.11. Laſtly, this Viſion they ſaw when they were in the Temple, not in a Cloyſter, a Barne, a Wood, a Conuenticle, and they were in the Temple with one accord too, with one Office, one Spirit, one Minde, one Faith; not heere a <hi>Separatist,</hi> there a <hi>Brownist,</hi> yonder a <hi>Familist,</hi> neere him an <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> but as their Faith was one, ſo was their life, and (if brought to the teſt) their death too. That was not <hi>Religion</hi> with them which was deuided,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lin. lib <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> nor that <hi>not vnity of opinion</hi> which they would not burne for. Some <hi>Heathens</hi> haue ſhewed ſuch reſolution and truth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in their <hi>falſe Religion;</hi> ſuch were thoſe - <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uales Sacerdotes</hi> - of olde amongſt the <hi>Romaines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caeſar lib. <hi>3.</hi> Galli.</note> the <hi>Solduni</hi> amongſt the <hi>Aquitans;</hi> the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> alſo had their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo called, becauſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25625:23"/>enioying each others benefites, as in one <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo in one Loue, they would dye together; ſuch were the <hi>Hunnes, Hyberi, Cantabri,</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>26.</hi> &amp; Cap. <hi>12.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> which were joynt-ſharers of each others miſeries, and fortunes; and if one by diſaſter or diſeaſe met with Calamitie, or Fate, the other ſought it. —</p>
               <q>— Placidam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> petunt pro vulnera mortem.</q>
               <p>If in matters therefore as well Morrall as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, there was ſuch reciprocation of old; and not onely in <hi>Religions,</hi> which were tainted, and ſmelt not of the true GOD, but in that too which hath beene touched and influenced by the <hi>Spirit of the Almightie,</hi> there was ſuch punctuall correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence then, why ſuch combuſtion now? Why thoſe dayly ſcarres and wounds both by the Tongue, and Penne? Why ſo much gall in our Pulpit, ſuch wormewood at the Preſſe? Why thoſe <hi>Ciuill-warres</hi> in our owne tenents? Such ſtabbings in particular opinions? Such heart-burnings in our <hi>Brethren?</hi> to the great diſquiet of our Mother, Church, and her Sonne they ſo labour to diſinherit, the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the wounded <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> who hath beene now ſo long Crucified betweene the - <hi>non - Conformiſt</hi> and the <hi>Romanist,</hi> that at length hee is inforced to flye to <hi>Caeſar</hi> for ſanctuary, and in the very reſcue and <hi>Appeale,</hi> like the poore man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Jerico, hee falls into the hands of Thieues,</hi> two deſperate cut-throates and enemies to the Truth, and him, the <hi>Pelagian</hi> and the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi> But no more (beloued) of thoſe Daggers and Stillettoes to our owne breſts by the cruelty of our owne <hi>Tribe;</hi> Know, diſſention is the very gate of ruine, and the breach at which deſtruction enters.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25625:24"/>Ciuill-warres are as dangerous in matters of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> as <hi>State,</hi> and proue the Earth-quakes both of Church and Common-wealth. The ſtory of the <hi>Romanes ſhafts</hi> is both old, and troden, but very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; <hi>in the Bundle they neuer felt injury of hand, one by one were the conqueſt of a finger,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Apronius</hi> Souldiers; - <hi>Satis validi ſi ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul,</hi> &amp;c. as long as they marched in their combined rankes they ſtood aloofe all danger, but, theſe deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they grew the prey and ſlaughter of the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; and thus - <hi>Dùm ſinguli pugnunt, vniuerſi vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur.</hi> A mutiny or rent in an Army <hi>is the Souldiers paſſing-bell,</hi> Death followes, or diſpaire of victory, when thoſe which are knit-vp in one heart of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and affection trample on diſtruſt as if they had already worne the palme and glory of their Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. And it ſpeeds no better in a deuided Church, where <hi>Sciſmes</hi> and <hi>Factions</hi> like ſo many <hi>rents</hi> and <hi>breaches,</hi> haue hewed-out, a way to her ouerthrow and ruine. No more <hi>ſtruglings</hi> then by vnnaturall <hi>twinnes</hi> in the <hi>wombe</hi> of our <hi>Rebecca.</hi> No more warre in her members, no more <hi>Bablings</hi> in their tongue, no more venome in their Penne, to the great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the <hi>Aduerſary,</hi> whoſe artillery is ready, his bow bent, the arrow on the ſtring and malice leuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the very boſome of the <hi>Church,</hi> (I pray God, not of the <hi>State</hi> too) and waites onely opportunity to looſen it. But <hi>let vs with all humbleneſſe of mind, meekeneſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. ver. 2.3.4.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>long ſuffering (ſupperting one another through loue) endeauour to keepe the vnity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of peace, knowing there is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one GOD, and Father of all, who is aboue all, through all, and in you all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now PAVL hath bin at <hi>Athens,</hi> paſt his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25625:24"/>bickerings with the <hi>Epicure,</hi> and the <hi>Stoicke,</hi> had their cenſure, - <hi>Hee is a Babler.</hi> - He is now rigged for <hi>Corinth,</hi> and by this time arriued there, where I leaue him - <hi>Jn earneſt Diſputation with the Graecians in the Synagogue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 19.5.</note> The <hi>Stoicke</hi> is returned to his <hi>Porch</hi> too, the <hi>Epicure</hi> to his <hi>Garden.</hi> But heere is an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> too, though no PAVL, or at leaſt no ſuch <hi>Paul;</hi> and yonder ſits a <hi>Stoicke</hi> and hee whiſpers to his <hi>Epicure,</hi> - What will <hi>this Babler</hi> ſay? He ſayes - <hi>Glory to GOD on high, in Earth peace, goodwill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</hi> Hee ſayes, hearty and true Allegeance to his Soueraigne, - wiſhes the budding and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a temporall Crowne heere, and the aſſurance of an immortall one hereafter. - Hee ſayes, floriſhing to his Church, his Common-wealth, his People; ſwift and fierce deſtruction to his Enemies foraigne, and (if hee haue any ſuch) domeſtique. - Hee ſayes courage to his Nobility, vnity to his Clergie, loue to his Gentry, loyaltie to his Commonalty. In fine; Hee ſayes proſperity to <hi>Athens</hi> (heere) vnanimity, true brotherhood, happie ſucceſſe to your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to your deſignes; and <hi>The grace of our Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST <hi>to you all, and with you all.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
